<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://emilevankrieken.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://emilevankrieken.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-10-17T13:31:00+00:00</updated><id>https://emilevankrieken.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">How I use Obsidian for academic work</title><link href="https://emilevankrieken.com/blog/2025/academic-obsidian/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How I use Obsidian for academic work"/><published>2025-10-16T10:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-16T10:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://emilevankrieken.com/blog/2025/academic-obsidian</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://emilevankrieken.com/blog/2025/academic-obsidian/"><![CDATA[<p>I am a big of <a href="https://obsidian.md/">Obsidian</a>. This used to be some niche tool five years ago, but now it seems like every new PhD student comes in with Obsidian installed. And for good reason! It is an extremely powerful tool for managing your academic knowledge work. I’ve been using Obsidian since 2020 (COVID…) and have optimised my workflow over many years. I also developed and contributed to <a href="https://github.com/HEmile/juggl">several</a> <a href="https://github.com/mdelobelle/obsidian_supercharged_links">popular</a> <a href="https://github.com/SkepticMystic/breadcrumbs">plugins</a> in the meantime! As many colleagues asked me about my Obsidian setup, I finally got around to writing about it.</p> <p>There are many blogs and videos about how to use Obsidian. Many of them are good, but I could not link to one to explain my system as it is not based on any popular system like Zettlekasten-based note-taking or an existing template. However, my setup is battle-tested in real-world academic use. I added <strong>2000+ papers</strong> across <strong>1000+ topics</strong> (and growing!) to my vault. The vault is centered on optimising for retrieval, and every day I exploit the knowledge graph I built over my career. Furthermore, my setup is technically quite minimal, and instead is centred around structuring your notes for effective academic work. In practice, only 2 community plugins are important!</p> <p><img src="/assets/img/obsidian-screenshot.png" alt="Obsidian screenshot" style="width:100%; height:auto;"/></p> <p>In this blog post, I’ll overview my Obsidian vault. This post is not an introduction to Obsidian. For the basics, there are many good resources, in particular the <a href="https://help.obsidian.md/install">Obsidian Help vault</a>. Finally, this setup is what works for me. You can read this blog post as a starting point, or just integrate some of its ideas into your own vault. But play around with it, and see what sticks!</p> <h1 id="the-high-level-overview">The high-level overview</h1> <p>I prepared a <a href="https://github.com/HEmile/academic-obsidian">template on Github</a> with everything installed and configured, and with a few example notes (sneaking in some shameless self-promotion of my work ;)). If you want to see some examples, download it, and open it as a folder in Obsidian. Then browse around a bit, both in the file browser and using backlinks.</p> <p>The central idea behind my vault is to build a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knowledge_graph">knowledge graph</a> out of your notes. Each note is a node in the graph with a particular type, and links between nodes are typed to have a particular meaning. Let’s start with the main types, which I indicate using tags.</p> <ul> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#source/paper</code> indicates notes about papers. Here, I will summarise and criticise the papers I’m reading <em>in my own words and understanding</em>.</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#source/talk</code> is similar, but for talks I attended.</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#topic</code> indicates the note is about a high-level topic. Papers and talks can be about that topic.</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#concept</code> are notes about particular concepts relevant in your field. I use them to define concepts and define their relationship to other concepts.</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#project</code> are notes about projects you are working on. I use them to keep track of the progress of my projects and ideas (these get the tag <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#project/idea</code>).</li> </ul> <p>I will introduce other types of notes as we go along.</p> <p>The central point of the vault is to <strong>link maximally</strong> between notes. This greatly increases the discoverability of your notes. So, seriously: For every paper you read and want to refer in your notes, create a note, link to it. For every concept you want to discuss, link to it with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">[[convex set]]</code>, even if you never create that note yet. Link everything! Linking greatly pays off because you can use <a href="https://help.obsidian.md/plugins/backlinks">Backlinks</a> to discover related notes and find (or more likely, rediscover) connections between your ideas and understanding.</p> <p>I only use tags to indicate note types, but never for anything semantic. I do not use any folder structure. Folders are strictly hierarchical, and creates walls between ideas. Furthermore, it is not worth the effort when you are already using links to structure your vault.</p> <h1 id="types-of-notes">Types of notes</h1> <p>Next, I’ll go in more detail for each type of note and how I link them together. For each, I will provide an example from the <a href="https://github.com/HEmile/academic-obsidian">template on Github</a>.</p> <h2 id="paper-notes-blue">Paper notes (blue)</h2> <p><img src="/assets/img/paper-example.png" alt="Paper note" style="width:60%; height:auto;"/></p> <p>Here is an example of a note about a paper (of mine). The title of the note is always just the title of the paper (I do the same for talks). Then, you can see a whole bunch of metadata (<a href="https://help.obsidian.md/properties">Properties</a>).</p> <ul> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">aliases</code>: <a href="https://help.obsidian.md/aliases">Aliases</a> is probably the <strong>most underused but powerful feature</strong> in core Obsidian. They allow you to create multiple names for a note. That is specifically very useful because when you are writing a note and want to link to some concept, you can open brackets with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">[[</code>, and aliases will come up as suggestions in case you use a different spelling, a related term, or a synonym. Aliases also allow you to group together related concepts into a single note, such as when a paper introduces a new concept. Finally, Obsidian can show unlinked mentions of aliases among the backlinks to improve the linking between notes.</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">hasTopic</code>: This is the first example of a <strong>typed link</strong> between notes, where the link type <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">hasTopic</code> provides additional semantic information about the link. It is the most important property for discoverability. I often have practically empty paper notes with just this field filled in so that it is indexed and easy to find. Note that you can include multiple topics in this field!</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">author</code>: A typed link to author notes, indicating they authored the paper. Author notes are just notes with the tag <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#author</code> and where they work. This may not seem that useful at first, but having author notes is very useful for networking! Whenever I am (re)meeting someone, I can check which of the papers I read and what I liked about them. This can also inspire useful new ideas for collaborations. I also use author notes to track where and when I met someone to reduce the amount of instances of “where did I know you from…”.</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">project</code>: This is a typed link to project notes for which the paper is relevant.</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">publishedIn</code>: This is a typed link to a note for the journal or conference in which the paper was published.</li> </ul> <p>After that comes the main note. In this example, I summarise the paper, linking to relevant concepts discussed in the meanwhile. I also often give my opinion of the paper for future reference.</p> <p>This might sound like a lot of work to manage for each paper, but plugins like <a href="https://github.com/SilentVoid13/Templater">Templater</a> and, in particular, <a href="https://github.com/hans/obsidian-citation-plugin">the citations plugin</a> make this seamless. I will explain in the Plugins section below how I set those up.</p> <h2 id="topic-notes-orange">Topic notes (orange)</h2> <p><img src="/assets/img/topic-example.png" alt="Topic note" style="width:89%; height:auto;"/></p> <p>Most of my topic notes are very simple, containing at best a few sentences to describe and define the topic, preventing confusion with other topics. The most important typed link for topic notes is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">subset</code>, which creates a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taxonomy">taxonomy</a> of topics (to be more precise, a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Directed_acyclic_graph">DAG</a>). For example, the topic of reasoning shortcuts studies a specific problem within neurosymbolic learning. And this problem relates to identifiability. Identifiability is actually a concept note, so I am not that strict about the function of each type of note and do whatever is fast and works best.</p> <p>When you use <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">hasTopic</code> from papers and talks to topic notes, they will appear automatically in the backlinks of the topic notes!</p> <h2 id="concept-notes-green">Concept notes (green)</h2> <p><img src="/assets/img/concept-example.png" alt="Concept note" style="width:70%; height:auto;"/></p> <p>Concept notes describe and define concepts. I use an exorbitant number of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">aliases</code>, as you can see in this example: A monotone function, for example, can be monotone because it is increasing or decreasing. It is really not needed to make separate concepts for those, as these concepts are highly related and should be grouped together. I mainly use two types of typed links: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">hasTopic</code> indicates the field of study that this concept is relevant for, and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">isA</code> provides a hierarchy of concepts. In this example, monotonicity is studied within mathematics, but a monotone function is a particular type of function.</p> <h2 id="project-notes-red">Project notes (red)</h2> <p><img src="/assets/img/project-example.png" alt="Project note" style="width:70%; height:auto;"/></p> <p>Project notes will discuss the progress of an ongoing project, or describe an idea for a new project (in which case they get the tag <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#project/idea</code>). I use the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">with</code> typed link to refer to author notes of people involved in the project. I also use this to indicate who I had some idea with. This saves you from going behind someones back on their own idea because you forgot where you got it from. Now you can see who I had the idea with, and who I can ask for a collaboration, help or feedback! (This might sound like a niche thing, but as you progress your career, you will thank me for this tip.) Such notes also have the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">hasTopic</code> typed link as usual, and I use a lot of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">aliases</code> for rediscoverability of ideas.</p> <p>For ideas, I also have a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">score</code> property to rank them in 1-5 (I rerank them every year or so when I have to decide on master thesis topics). And another for the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">size</code> of the idea.</p> <h1 id="plugins">Plugins</h1> <p>Plugins in Obsidian are oft-discussed, with some people using 100+ plugins and chasing the latest cool features. I… somewhat used to be one of these people, but at this point core Obsidian is progressed so far that you rarely need them for the majority of common workflows. I will next discuss some plugins I use on a daily basis, and a few optional ones that might suit your workflow.</p> <h2 id="supercharged-links"><a href="https://github.com/mdelobelle/obsidian_supercharged_links">Supercharged Links</a></h2> <p>This is my favourite plugin - but I also contributed heavily to it, so I might be a bit biased. You might have noticed from my examples that links have different colours depending on the type of note they are. This is because of this plugin! It’s honestly a huge life-saver: When I scroll through a search, or look at a note, I can immediately see if it is a paper, a concept, a project, etc. So when I search for something specific, I can open the quick switcher and visually filter by one of the colours without having to type an explicit filter.</p> <p>In addition, I programmed a few extras for this vault, such as that paper notes automatically indicate the year of publication and the venue they were published in. And for ideas, it shows the score I assign to it. Setting this up is not hard, but requires a bit of tweaking with CSS. I would suggest to start with the <a href="https://github.com/HEmile/academic-obsidian">template</a> and work from there.</p> <h2 id="citations"><a href="https://github.com/hans/obsidian-citation-plugin">Citations</a></h2> <p>The citations plugins are known for their integration with Zotero or bibtex files. That is what I also used… But honestly, it was too slow. Waiting for Zotero to import a file took too long, and so did syncing that with Obsidian.</p> <p>Instead, I use a custom-built version of this plugin available <a href="https://github.com/HEmile/academic-obsidian/tree/main/.obsidian/plugins/obsidian-citation-plugin">here</a>, which is preinstalled in the <a href="https://github.com/HEmile/academic-obsidian">template</a>. This adds a new command and hotkey to <strong>directly create a paper note from a bibtex entry on your clipboard</strong>. Then, I just find a bibtex entry online, copy it, hit the hotkey, and voila! This automatically adds the year, authors and citekey.</p> <h2 id="other-useful-plugins">Other useful plugins</h2> <ul> <li>Templater: Just a must-have plugin. I use it more extensively for my personal vault, but here it’s still very useful for automatically adding timestamps to my notes and getting cursors on the right place.</li> <li>Extended MathJax: Allows you to add a preamble for your latex. I use this a lot for eg boldfaced math.</li> <li>Omnisearch: A replacement for the built-in search. It’s blazing fast and clear, and works on PDFs.</li> <li>Pane relief: This is such a staple for me that I always forget what it does unless I turn it off and get super frustrated. Try it out!</li> <li>Paste URL into selection: Simple, select some text, insert a link to it by pasting.</li> </ul> <h2 id="optional-plugins">Optional plugins</h2> <p>Here are some other plugins I played with that are good, but did not end up being core to my workflow. If there is one I would recommend out of these, it is Breadcrumbs… Please read on.</p> <ul> <li>(Core) You’ll need some way to sync and backup your vault. I just use <a href="https://help.obsidian.md/sync">Obsidian Sync</a>. It has never failed me.</li> <li>(Core) Bases: This is a new feature to create database-like views from your notes. I haven’t played around with it enough to see if it’ll stick, but it sure is well-built! However, many people seem to rely on it. The setup I described above actually barely relies on it - The core navigation and search is really based on the graph structure (ie, navigating links in notes and navigating backlinks). Therefore, I only end up using database-like views for specific use cases like reranking ideas.</li> <li>(Core) Canvas, Graph view: Honestly, these are fun to play with, but I never use them. GUI-based things are just too slow compared to plain text and keyboard shortcuts.</li> <li>(Core) Bookmarks: Interesting feature, but I tried it a bit and rarely</li> <li>(Core) VIM support: I love VIM. If you like VIM as well, activate it. The VimRC plugin is a great complement.</li> <li><a href="https://github.com/SkepticMystic/breadcrumbs">Breadcrumbs plugin</a>: This plugin is <strong>insane</strong>. It allows for truly navigating your notes as a graph (more specifically, a DAG). Why is this useful in this setup? Well, let’s say you want to find all papers about the topic <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Artificial Intelligence</code>. Currently, you could navigate to that note, and find the backlinks to it. But, then you would be missing papers that link to the subtopic <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Neurosymbolic Artificial Intelligence</code> but not to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Artificial Intelligence</code>. With Breadcrumbs, you can actually hierarchically navigate through your vault, and also find the papers about <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Neurosymbolic Artificial Intelligence</code> within a single list. Really really powerful. In practice, I end up not using it as frequently as I thought I would. However, every now and then you <em>really</em> need it, and then you’ll seriously appreciate it.</li> <li><a href="https://github.com/HEmile/juggl">Juggl plugin</a>: This is an advanced graph view plugin I developed. You might expect me to use this a lot… But honestly, it was just too slow and clunky for daily use. Fun to play around with, and it might work for you, but I wouldn’t necessarily recommend it.</li> <li><a href="https://github.com/RyotaUshio/obsidian-pdf-plus">PDF++ plugin</a>: Many people annotate their PDFs in Obsidian and try to link it together. I find it too cumbersome for the vast majority of papers, but this plugin really is excellent if you do prefer that workflow.</li> </ul> <p>Oh, about LLM plugins: I don’t use them. I might integrate one if there’s one that can understand the hierarchical structure of my notes via some RAG system, but right now it’s not good enough. And seriously, <strong>do not use LLMs to write your notes</strong>. The whole point of taking notes is to write them in your own words and understanding, and to go back and view what <strong>you</strong> understood about it, not an LLM. (I am not an LLM hater at all, I use them all the time for QA, coding and assisted writing, just never in Obsidian.)</p> <h2 id="hotkeys">Hotkeys</h2> <p>Some important hotkeys that come pre-installed with the <a href="https://github.com/HEmile/academic-obsidian">template</a>:</p> <ul> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cmd + O</code>: Open quick switcher</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cmd + control + O</code>: Open omnisearch</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cmd + P</code>: Open command palette</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">control + option + shift + I</code>: Create paper note from clipboard containing bibtex</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cmd + R</code>: Insert template</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">control + O</code>: Navigate backward</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">control + I</code>: Navigate forward</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cmd + J</code>: Hide/show left sidebar</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cmd + K</code>: Hide/show right sidebar</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="productivity"/><category term="productivity"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This post gives an overview of how I use Obsidian for academic research work. I use it to manage papers, talks, topics, concepts and projects in a Knowledge Graph-inspired setup.]]></summary></entry></feed>